[music]
So memories is a bad name. Uh it's a
it's a it's a joke. I was trying to
prove a point and I was trying to be
cool. I was trying to prove a point to
some of my colleagues and uh teammate
>> teammates on where the space of agent
memory is going and is that I created a
library around about a year ago and I
created it so that I can essentially
communicate in code where I see a lot of
um agentic engineering going towards. So
most pe some most of you will
know
at a high level what I'm talking about.
Some of you might have already heard
some tools like mem zero. Anyone heard
of me zero hair? Put your hand up. Two.
That's good. Like 0.1% or something. Um
anyone heard of uh Langme?
No. Lang graph. Anyone heard of
langraph? Yes. Anyone heard of lang
chain? Yes. Okay. So, Langme is the
memory management uh layer for built by
the team at Langchain. So, you can check
it out. Um, so everything I'm talking
about today, there are teams in the
front line that are exploring how to
really make agent memory work. So, the
maybe the reason why you've not heard of
Lang MEM is because it's still in in
development, but a lot of people have
heard of me zero. They just raised
another big round recently. Um, anyone
heard of me GPT?
Yeah, that's good. Letter is is the
commercial name. That's excellent. So,
my name is Richmond Richmond and today
I'm going to be talking to you about
memory engineering and I'm going to be
talking to you about memory engineering
through uh the library that I built
called memories. So, the way we're going
to split this workshop is uh hopefully
um the time and work works. We're going
to use 30 minutes to talk about memory
engineering agent memory. We'll start
from high level then we'll work our way
down into the technicalities of it. Then
we'll spend the rest 1 hour 30 minutes
really going through some code and
hopefully the code works as well and you
guys can also follow along. Um there's a
bunch of instructions. The repo is open
source and I will show you the notebooks
where you can follow along and if things
don't work you can I can come over and
help you and guide you or you can do
this in your free time and reach out to
me on LinkedIn and we can talk about
agent memory and memory engineering and
pancakes. I'm a big fan of pancakes. Um,
I know the best I know the best pancake
spot in the UK if you ever visit and I'm
I'm open to recommendations for New
York. So, let's start. What are you
going to learn from this workshop? Uh, a
lot of it is my propaganda which is
fair. Um, well, it was propaganda last
year. This year is uh people are
starting to see where the space is
going. So, we're going to understand the
architecture of agent memory. We're
going to understand different types of
memory. We're going to really bring this
high level concept of memory that we've
been hearing a lot. Um,
uh, folks at Google recently put out a
paper called context engineering session
in memory, but most of it was memory
engineering and not a lot of context
engineering there. So, this is really
topical and it's really good to
understand why agent memory and what
it's actually trying to solve. Then
we'll talk about the data to memory
pipeline. When does data become memory
is a question that a lot of people have
asked me. We'll talk about the different
memory types. So long-term memory,
short-term, episodic, semantic,
conversational, and we'll also talk
about how we can implement some of these
memory engineering patterns. We'll talk
about it at high level. Then we'll look
at the code and see what we've been able
to do with memories. and we'll build an
agent architecture by uh backed by a
memory core. And when I say memory core,
the memory core that we're using today
is going to be Oracle. It's going to be
Oracle AI database. So there's a bunch
there's a lot of information here today.
And I want to get to the code section.
In the code, we're going to see a single
agent that we're going to augment with
memory. Then there's another second
coding session where we'll look at like
a deep research use case where we will
get an agent that can do a that can
generate a bunch of reports and spawn
other agents. So we'll go through this
and there is one worry. Can I show you
can I share with you the one worry that
I have? I am going to be running through
the code but I feel like this was this
is too small for you guys to see. So
hopefully we'll we'll we'll figure
something that works. If not, um, all
the code is online and you can follow
along. So, let's get started. Number
one, AI agents. What's an AI agent? And
has everyone heard about AI agents,
right? Hands up if you heard of AI
agents.
Excellent. And I I'll guess the ones
that didn't put your hands up, you're
just too lazy to put your hands up. Um,
cuz agent this year is like what this
the who said this word? Um, it's the
decade of AI agents. Who said it? uh I
think Andre Kapathy said it in a in a
podcast um is the decade of AI agents
and I agree. So what's an AI agent?
Well, an AI agent is a computational
entity that basically can act
independently. Uh that's the that's the
goal. It has uh it is backed by some
form of LLM and the LLM helps it with
its cognitive abilities which would
involve include reasoning. It also can
take um actions through tool use or
function calling and it's al it also can
take um it also can perceive his
environment right but the most important
part of an agent is it can it is
augmented by memory it has a form of
memory now um I'm biased I work in a I
work in a database division within
Oracle and I've worked in different
other database companies but my bias My
my opinion is you can't have an agent
without memory. It's like the the way I
try to describe it, it's like how many
of you have ever bought a house before
or even just rented one? Hands up.
Great. So imagine you're like a estate
agent and you were telling them um it's
Monday and told them the type of house
you wanted, the budget, where you'd like
to live, your family size, what you
would like to avoid and all the good
stuff. Then this this is on Monday. Then
you get to Tuesday and you meet the same
estate agent and they forget who you
are. You have to reintroduce yourself
and you have to tell them your budget,
where you like to live and your family
size and things you like to avoid. And
then you get to Wednesday, you meet the
same estate agent and they forget who
you are and you have to repeat the same
thing over and over again. That gets
annoying, right? You're not going to use
that estate agent. Well, the same goes
for this computational form of agents.
They're meant to act independently,
eventually act on our behalf. So we need
to make them more reliable, believable
and capable. So we need to make them
actually um perform in in production.
And the way that I think we should be
able to do that is by um obviously by
having better models but also by having
a form of memory uh augmented memory
that is uh connected to the agent. Okay.
So that is what's an agent. Um a
computational entity backed by memory
has perception of its environment can
take tools and has reasonabilities that
um that is uh provided by an LLM. Does
anyone There was once a time where we
couldn't agree on the definition of an
agent. Does anyone disagree with my
definition of an what an agent is? And
don't be shy. It's fine. This is a
conversation. You disagree. Why do you
disagree, sir? That's not really your
definition, but do you really believe
that they can reason?
>> Do I agree that they can reason?
>> Yeah.
Or is it just something that kind of
looks like
>> it? It kind of looks like reason. It's
mimicking reason. But let me ask you
another question. How do humans reason?
>> Poorly. Yeah. Especially me. But how do
human reason? Like, can you explain it
to me?
>> Evaluating like alternatives
like thinking in the sense of like
compare comparing preparing concepts
>> then that that's good. A better question
is do I need to do I need to stay so the
camera can see me?
>> No.
>> Okay. Oh, the m exc um a better question
um do you think humans understand how
the the human brain works 100%.
We don't. Neuroscience is still an
active field of development. We don't
essentially know how our brain works
uh uh as well as we know other parts of
our body. But I do agree with you. LLMs
are just mimicking. It's just next token
prediction. But hey, mimicry is the best
form of a flattery. So, um, okay. But
yeah, fair enough. And but that's not uh
that's that's if I was an open AI, maybe
I'll be able to rebutle that a little
bit better, but I'm an Oracle, so let's
go. Use cases for AI agent. Um, workflow
automation is the most popular one. uh
there's a bunch of processes that we
have in some of the systems and uh
pipelines or some of the tools we use
today and some of them can be very
manual.
One thing that we have agents and we've
used agents for is to automate
workflows.
So the agents can essentially take
decisions that based on some heristics
or some guard drills or something that
it's internal to it that has been
provided by a human to then make the
right decision. Then we have research
and analysis agent. So within uh chat
GPT and within Gemini you can go into
deep research mode and you can give it
some instructions and it will ask you
for some clarifications and then it will
go off to the internet and it will do a
bunch of research and analysis and be
able to give you a final report. So deep
research is a very research and analysis
agents are very common and it's a very
useful um use case for AI agents. Then
you have data knowledge retrieval. You
have coding and software engineering
agents. I'm a big fan of cursor. I I use
cursor. So that could be an example of
uh coding agents. Um then there are
customer supports and service agents
that we have in most of the customer um
facing industry or applications that we
have today. So again, personal
productivity agents. I use notion as
well, and they have this little AI
assistance that they try to get me to
use that I don't really use, but it's it
it's there. But um so there are
different types of agents, there are
different types of use cases for AI
agents, but in all of the variations of
AI agents, there are some common
patterns or common use cases and I call
them application modes. So they're
common application modes in AI agent.
The first one is assistant, right? Back
and forth conversational um assistant AI
agent and it would typically respond to
your query and it doesn't need to have a
robust um uh knowledge base and you can
think of um this as chat GPT chat is a
good example of an assistant. The next
one is workflow workflow agents. Um the
best way I can describe this is uh how
many of you have used uh the tool NA10?
So NA10 is used to like construct a
bunch of workflow then you can automate
it but you can actually do most of this
programmatically. So you can actually
have typical um you can use lang graph
to build a workflow to construct a
workflow and have um have it be LLM
driven essentially and it would have
sequential steps or processes that would
execute either sequentially or in
parallel. So that's workflow.
Then we spoke about deep research,
right? Uh deep research, I've explained
it already. So these are the three um
common application modes I'm seeing.
Assistant, workflow, deep research.
Assistant, workflow, deep research. So
again, does anyone disagree with me or
can anyone add sort of application modes
that you're seeing?
Do you all agree that this is this
captures a general pattern? Then
>> hands up if you agree.
>> Question.
>> Go on.
>> Where would you put coding?
>> I'll put
>> Oh.
>> Uh, where would you put coding
assistance into that? Because it feels
deeper than workflow, but not quite
research.
>> Yeah.
>> Um, it it sits between.
>> So, what was the start of your question?
Repeat it. Where would you put coding
agents? Yeah.
>> Into this taxonomy.
>> Okay. So, I would put coding agents into
the assistant column. So, earlier this
year, I used to think you're either one
or the other. You're either an assistant
or you're either a workflow or you're
either deep researched. And I sat with a
professor based there in uh New York. it
came to London and we're having
conversation in in the UK um in about
data and agents and over pancakes
obviously is how I have all my
conversations and he changed my mind he
said Richmond you shouldn't see so
binary right um an agent can fall within
a spectrum of these application mode so
it's just the the level of um the
application mode it has and it got me
thinking is it you can almost imagine it
as Uh, does anyone know the Maya Briggs
personalities? Do you guys know it?
Yeah. Good. So, I am a INTJ, which is
like the architect, rightfully so. Um,
but human personality, you're not just
one or the other. There's a there's a
scale of different characteristics, and
that's why I looked at it. So, earlier
this year, you're either one or the
other. Now, it's a spectrum, right? It's
different um characteristics of this. So
to answer your question, where would you
put a coding agent? Well, a coding agent
is going to have it. It's not going to
have deep research for sure. It's going
to have a bit of the spectrum of
assistant and workflow. A coding agent
can traverse through a bunch of files
and can search the internet, but deep
research is extensive. It it goes into
different online sources, then goes
within nested links and all all the site
cited links within the initial source
link. So I wouldn't put a coding agent
within the deep research um column. So I
would say it has a a balance between
assistant and maybe some workflows as
well.
Again, this is a conversation. I love it
when people disagree with me. Um this is
how I know I'm doing a a bad job. If
everyone agrees with me, that means I'm
doing a very terrible job. So please
let's let's learn together and grow
together. Um agent memory. So, we're
here at the key part and I'll try to uh
be on time here. So, 10:25. And I can
see my internet has died. So, I'll have
to connect to the one that um Alan told
us to connect to. But I'll do that when
we get into the code, not now cuz the
slides are loaded. They work offline.
Yay, Google. Um so, agent memory. So,
I'm going to define in this section. I'm
going to define what agent memory is. a
agent memory is we're also going to talk
about the different types of agent
memory and I'll give some very high
level description but when we get to the
code it's going to make sense.
So I want to start with humans. Um
humans are a very good example and it
makes it easy to understand what I'm
talking about when we get to the
computational form of all of the memory
types we're going to be talking about.
So humans have a very good ability some
anyway have good abilities to retain
reuse and recall information and humans
are nature is a very great architect of
intelligence and we've used nature as a
blueprint for technology. So if you look
at the airplanes the earlier um attempts
at building airplanes took inspirations
from um uh birds of flight right and
insects. So the first iterations were uh
devices that mimicked flapping. Again,
mimicry is the best form of flattery.
We're mimicking um the way uh birds were
flying. We didn't end up with airplanes
that that flat. The the plane that took
over here didn't flap its wings. It was
a turbulent um air air uh it was a
turbulent flight. There was a lot of
turbulence, but it didn't flap its
wings. Thank god. Um but the key thing
is even within agent memory we can also
look to humans to the human brain in
particular how it works how it function
and take inspiration from it to actually
understand how can we augment our agents
with computational form of memory. So
these are examples of memory in humans.
So we have working memory, we have
long-term memory, we have short-term
memory. So I could tell you my phone
number now. I'm not going to do that.
But I could tell you now, but you would
have remember by the end of this um uh
talk or we do you wouldn't remember the
next two hours except if you wrote it
down. Uh but if you were to repeat it to
yourself maybe 10 20 times then it will
probably go into a more longer form of
memory within your brain and then you
probably able to remember. Uh we have
episodic memory. Uh we have semantic
memory. So um we have associative
memory. So if I tell you to think about
the color red, think about the color
red.
Okay, I'm going to assume you thought
about it. So, some of you would have
thought about blood, maybe roses, um, or
other things associated with the color
red, associative memory. Some of you
might have good recollections of
birthdays that you've had. Um, that is a
form of episodic memory as well. Um, my
ones are are good, all good, thank god.
Um, okay. So, this can help inspire
agent memory. And when I used to do this
talk, I used to have a bunch of image
explaining what agent memory is and I
used to just go straight into it. But
now uh the past couple months I've I've
realized that I need to explain what is
agent memory uh very clear and agent
memory is has different components to
it. So it needs to have an external
store, right? Agent memory needs to have
an external store. So this is going to
be like a database or a file system. Um
well a database cuz I'm biased. So you
need to have a database. You also need
to have um agent memory also consists of
the context window of the LLM that is
part of the agent's memory because
remember an agent as an LLM that
provides the reasoning and cognitive
abilities. Then the parametric the
parametric memory of the LLM that is
static which means it doesn't change
that's also agent memory as well. So an
agent has this external database
um that could be dynamic form of memory
has this working memory with in the form
of it context window then has this
parametric memory in the in the weights
and parameters of the model itself. So
those are the main components of agent
memory and memory engineering is all of
the code that we write to move
information through this component.
That's what memory engineering is. So I
hope that's very clear and I've kind of
just summarized all the talk in that one
sentence. So we're going to go through
the slides. Um, but this is a much uh
better definition of what agent memory
is. And agent memory is and the one the
the phrase I find that explains it is is
that it's a computational exocortex for
AI agents. That's how I is best to
explain it. And also the way I explained
it is also a good way to explain it. And
the key thing about agent memory and the
aim where we're trying to get to is we
want to make AI agents more reliable,
believable, and capable. So, everyone
understands reliability, right? You want
to be able to use the same a AI agents
over and over again, and you can rely on
it to give you the right answer the same
way you would go to your doctor and you
rely on them to give you the best
medicine um for certain disease.
Sometimes um but yeah, capability as
well. Uh you want your AI agents to be
capable. You want them to be robust and
be able to do uh you expect them to do
what you ask them to do. And you want
them to be you want them to be
believable as well. Now the is quick
question. Is believability a word? I
should have Googled this before I
started this talk. It's a word, right?
Hands up if it's a word. Nice. Thank
you. So the believability of a an agent
is actually quite important especially
if you have one that is meant to be an
assistant, one that is meant to interact
with humans. So the la the latest update
from chat really honed in on that
believability factor, right? Because now
you can change the personality of you
could change the personas within chat
GPT. Now has anyone tried that out yet?
Yeah, I haven't tried it out either, but
you can change the personality of chat
GPT now. So that's a bit the
believability factor and we're going to
look at the memory types that help each
of these factor actually work in AI
agent. So we're going to go into type of
agent memory. So there are three main
type short-term, long-term and
coordination. coordination is actually
quite special because we need it during
um multi- aent um multi- aent
architectures as as we are going to see
in deep research mode.
So the first uh the first aspect of this
are the different types of short-term
and long-term and shared memory. So
working memory is very obvious right is
this short-term uh short-term form of
memory. Uh so is semantic cache as well.
semantic hash. We're going to look at
all of this in code examples as well.
There is proc procedural memory which is
essentially skills and routines. Um you
can think of information as to what MCP
to use if you were to store that
information in a database. That would be
a form of procedural memory. Um you
could think about storing all the JSON
schema of like REST APIs and all the
functions you have that you want your
your AI agents to call. That's a form of
procedural memory. Workflow memory. So
remember I mentioned that you could
there free application mode and one of
them was workflow. So you can actually
have the steps that an AI agent takes
when executing a task you can store that
into a database or some form of external
memory store and in the next iteration
whether the task was successful or it
was a failure that's experience for the
next iteration of the agent. So it can
call it it can actually use the steps
that were successful or have reasons for
failures and try to avoid that path or
take a different um path. So that's
workflow memory. Uh we're going to go uh
through each of this in more detail. Now
this is going to get annoying because I
have animations here that are necessary.
Uh but we I'll click through very
quickly. So short-term memory.
Short-term memory is this the there are
different types of short-term memory.
But the key thing here is they don't
last long. They're not for long arriving
task. The the information stored in
short-term memory is meant to be cleared
after a certain time or maybe when there
is seems to be some lack of activity,
you would remove the information within
the short-term memory. So a very common
uh short-term memory is working memory.
So then we have long-term memory.
Long-term memory, as obvious, is meant
to persist through sessions. It's meant
to persist through act um in activity in
within your application. And you
actually want to you could use long-term
memory across sessions as well. And then
for coordination, which is particularly
shared memory, there's a special type of
memory that you need within multi- aent
um architectures or agents where you
have multiple agents working together.
And it's just a way to say, hey, I have
this external store that is just going
to be used for information that is
involved within multiple agents talking
and all of multiple agents working
together. And all of these agents can
work within the same memory space in a
sense. So it's usually called as a
blackboard is what you would call it.
And you have all of the agents
communicating and pulling information in
and out of this memory space. Now there
are different ways you can architect
communication in mult multi- aent
architectures but one of the common ways
to have them share context which
obviously for obvious reasons it can uh
cause a lot of problems that will lead
you into the path of context engineering
techniques or you can have them just
share instructions. So you have a root
agent giving only instructions to the
sub aents as opposed to sharing all the
context and back back and forth as well.
So there are again unnecessary
animations. I apologize for that. We're
just going to go over to the just click
through. Excellent. So working in
memory. Work in memory are again
temporary. They usually you can think of
it as the agent scratchpad. And a good
example of working in memory is uh the
LLM context window. Right? That is a a
good example of working in memory. We're
using that we're using that context
window in the moment as this agent
scratchbad to do things like um chain uh
chain of thought right uh that's being
done in the agent's working memory then
session memory so if you go through and
this is where I guess this is how you
know the field is still developing uh
when Google put out their technical
white paper there it was it was very
good I read it on the flight hair um it
was very good it covered a lot of
information. It also expanded my
thinking into some aspect of agent
memory that I've not yet considered. But
one thing I didn't agree with is they
saw session and memory as two different
[clears throat] two distinct things. Um
and they they they defined it and to me
that was weird because session is a type
of memory. You store information within
a session. It is short-term memory. And
uh in the paper when you uh read maybe
uh several pages down they do clarify
that a lot of people call session as
part of uh short-term memory. But I
think so the one place where I disagreed
with the white paper was you don't need
to actually separate the two. Session is
a type of short-term memory and then you
have other
forms of memory. So again the space is
still developing. A lot of people are
the best thing about this uh I guess
this era of AI and just AI in general is
everyone's learning and everyone is
sharing knowledge. So a lot of folks in
anthropic lang chain manus
Google and and wherever I am we share
the information that we're coming across
when we're trying to make this AI agent
uh AI agents more reliable believable
and capable. And I have to apologize. I
have a slight cough. [cough]
So I'll be coughing occasionally. Uh let
me skip over to semantic cache.
So does has anyone heard of caching?
Hands up. Hands down. Okay, that's
a decent enough you understand caching
while I explain semantic cache. And
we're going to see semantic cache in
action as well. Essentially, it's a way
to reduce the operational cost of your
AI agent. So generally
the way semantic cache works is it's a
form of short-term memory because you
can actually state the time to live for
information within a semantic cache
store. Um but essentially how it works
is you make within an iteration your
user or application
>> sorry what's it
>> cough cough. Oh
thank you very much. Um,
that's Am I that bad?
>> This free bottles of water. Excellent.
Okay, this is good. Um, all right.
[clears throat] I feel like I feel
better now. Um, okay. So, let's talk
about semantic cache very quickly. So,
when you make a call to uh LLM, you
would typically uh incur some charge on
the API side, right? On the inference
side. So you make your call to the LLM,
you get your user query, you make the
call to the LLM and you get some
response back. But what semantic cache
does is it actually stores the query and
it stores an embedding of the query and
also stores the response from the LLM
because when the user makes let's say in
the next execution the user makes a
similar question for example um I forgot
my password and I can't remember my
password are the same they would have
the same answer right and what you would
want is you don't want to go to an LLM
to like do the whole work again if
you've done it previously. What you want
to do is use the cache response because
there is this semantic similarity that
you've used techniques like vector
search to calculate the similarity
between the two queries and you've
noticed that they're quite similar. So
you use a a cached response. That's
that's a semantic um aspect of semantic
cache. So
next is um procedural memory. Right?
We've spoken about this. I'm not going
to go over it, but it's skills and
routines essentially, and we're going to
see examples of this as well. Episodic
memory is an interesting one, right? So,
the back and forth interactions that you
have with AI agents, that's a form of
episodic memory, right? Especially when
you add a time stamp to it. So, it means
that I can retrieve this aspect of
memory using some form of maybe um
timebased uh retrieval query or
something, right? Or it can also mean
that this memory component or memory
unit has a form of um a subject to it.
So summarization is a form of episodic
memory. Um so summarization is a context
engineering technique. Uh it's when you
have this context window uh the context
windows are bounded by token length and
so there's a context window limit. So
whenever you're approaching the context
window threshold, typically a technique
is to summarize um the existing content
within the context window and then pass
that into a clean context window and you
just have the summary then and you just
carry on the conversation. Now you would
notice a lot of uh cursor does this
because on the interface you can see the
percentage of your context window
utilization and in memories the library
that I created we actually calculate
this in every iteration as well uh
because it's it's useful for both the
human and it's also useful for the agent
as well because agents can you want to
be able to allow them to summarize their
own context um when doing execution so
you don't have uh context bloat
essentially. So within memories the
library uh the agents can actually
summarize their context as well
especially when you run them in deep
research mode.
So uh then we move on to semantic.
Semantic essentially types of semantic
memory are knowledge bases or entity
memory or personal memory. So knowledge
basis is uh knowledge base is
essentially um information that you have
about the world that is stored in an
external store. So for those of you that
have implemented retrieval augmented
generation or uh rack pipelines, you
would have used a form of knowledge base
to ground the response of the LLM in
some form of uh um uh relevant data.
That's that's an example of semantic
memory. Entity memory basically when
agents interact with other entities
within the environments that they
executing, you can store that
information in a memory store. So for
example, if I have an AI agent uh that
uh gaming is a good example for this. So
imagine you have a character in a game
and they interact with different
entities in the game. You can store the
information in a form in in your entity
memory store and update it as that uh as
your agent interacts with the same
character over time. Humans do this all
the time. So um we have information of
other people within our brain and their
characteristics.
So I've already explained shared memory
and I've explained most of the different
forms of um LLM context window and
different forms of memory. So allow me
to do something weird which is just skip
through all of this because the
animation order is not uh I could have
just closed this and skipped the slides.
The animation order is not right. So now
we can go into memory engineering. Now
this is the part where
this is a part where I would like us to
if we can discuss if we can discuss if
the things I'm saying to you sound more
like context engineering or does it
sound like do we need a new discipline
to define the work that we're doing. So
very quickly, I work with a lot of AI
teams and I've seen the things folks are
building and I've seen how they are
optimizing them and context engineering
is one of the tasks that I see a lot of
engineers doing. But then to improve the
latency of your retrieval pipelines,
you're going into things that look like
search optimization or if you're a
database engineer, right? you would know
things like prefiltering or post
filtering or you're just uh modifying
the query just to improve the latency
because eventually we want this AI
agents to work in real time and in
production environment. So you're going
to look at things like quantization of
your embedding models and making sure
you're using quantis indexes. So a lot
of the work I saw a lot of um engineers
doing were around more memory type
activities. In fact, a very large
company, recruiting company, um, they
have a specific AI memory team. The How
many people use cursor here?
That's good. A lot of people. The There
is I don't know if it's still the case,
but at some point this year, there was
only one person responsible for making
sure cursor is able to retain, recall,
and reuse information. And that person
on LinkedIn defines themselves it
defines himself as a memory engineer. So
again, still early days. It was early
days last year. We're still getting to
the point where people are beginning to
understand the job to be done. I already
defined what memory engineering was
earlier, but I'll do it again. So memory
engineering is the is the scaffolding
that we have to write to move
information from the components of agent
memory which is this external memory
store that could be a database or a file
system. It could be the LLM context
window and the parametric memory within
the LLM itself. So memory engineering is
all the harness and scaffolding that we
use to move data which I call memories
between these components. And there's
going to be a lot more content coming
out on memory engineering. And I like
talking about memory engineering because
it's sort of it's a it's an area of
agent engineering that feels like
everyone can participate in. Right? So
you can have one engineer at cursor or
like myself building these libraries and
frameworks or you can have a 100
engineers working on chatt or on claude
to make memory work but because it's not
yet solved. It's it's a place where you
can be creative
but also you can just constantly learn
and participate in
ideally getting us to what we can
describe as AGI. So
that's what memory engineering is. It's
the job to be done to me. it's the last
job to be done because once once we
solve memory um I think we're we're
going to be on a very uh uh exponential
path to a exponential trajectory to AGI
once our agents are able to remember
effectively well and they're reliable
believable and capable they would it
would give us a good path to to AGI so I
want to touch on prompt engineering and
context engineering and memory
engineering Now again, I like to be
interactive. I like to have
conversations. So I'm going to ask it
I'm going to ask a question and I'm
going to ask it now and I'm going to ask
it later on during at the end. Does
anyone put your hands up if you agree
with the distinction between memory
engineering and context engineering?
Are we getting there? We're getting
there. I see three people. Okay, put
your hands up if you agree with the
distinction between prompt engineering
and context engineering.
More people. That's good. This is good.
All right. So, prompt engineering, I see
it as, and I'll just go through this.
So, my aim is not to get everyone to put
their end their hand up after I'm done.
Um, I would like to get a few more hands
thin free. So, let's go. Uh, prompt
prompt engineering is very simple. Uh,
in fact, I could skip this this slide.
Actually, I'll just go straight to this
one. Prompt engineering is a
maximization technique, right? Because
what we're trying to do is get more
tokens into the context window to ensure
that the LLM gave us the right answer in
the right format. So, we had things like
few shot um few shot prompting, right?
Because then what we did there was give
the the LLM examples of outputs that we
expected and we also gave it examples of
inputs. And the more inputs and output
you gave it, the more uh essentially the
more it was able to um adear to whatever
format you expecting. So it's a
maximization technique, right? There was
this chain of thought um approach and
there is in context learning as well.
But the key thing is here we were we're
frontloading cognition.
So the LLMs we gave them more data, more
compute and they grew a lot bigger,
right? We increased the number of
parameters within this LLM and it
reduced the amount of prompt engineering
that we had to do to get what we wanted.
But then we found out that even though
we were increasing the context window of
these LLMs,
stuffing information in there going
using that maximization approach didn't
work. It didn't give you the I guess
what we can loosely describe as this
promise performance performance gain
because we had things issues like uh
needle in the hstack or loss in the
middle problem, right? So the more
information you gave this LLM, the
harder it was for them to remember
certain key information.
So um and you go into things like
context rot, you go you have context
bloating, confusion, all of this key
buzzwords. So context engineering and
anthropic define it best.
Essentially what context engineering is
is finding the configuration of the
optimal tokens to put into the context
window. Right? You it it's not putting
everything you can. It's just putting
the right thing. Essentially you're
trying to get the most bang for your
buck. Right? So it's an optimization
engineering. It's optimizing. Right? So
prompt engineering maximization context
engineering optimization. Now memory
engineering because we have this free
components that we're working with
within an agent within an agent and
we're trying to move information through
these um three components we actually
have to do a bit of optimization and
maximization.
So prompt uh memory engineering is
continuation and it's continuation
because what we're essentially doing is
uh the maximization aspect will come
into where you're taking things out of
the um out of the context window.
Sometimes you can augment this
information so you can enrich this
information so in the next iteration you
can actually have more I guess more
information to play with or more context
to play with to get your desired output.
But in the same aspect it's optimizing
because we have summarization technique
from context engineering that you can
store in uh in your memory uh store as
well. So you have to use some of this
summarization aspect is optimization as
well because we have to optimize the
retrieval pipelines. We have to think
about quantization. We have to do things
like um prefiltering, post filtering,
optimizing all the queries that we're
actually putting into that we're using
to retrieve information. So it's both
optimization and maximization
leading to continuation because we want
memory to persist and improve and
eventually our agents to learn and adapt
over time. So that's why prompt
engineering is maximization, context
engineering is optimization, memory
engineering is continuation.
I think you guys would get the slides um
as part of the question.
>> We need to use the mic.
>> Is it possible to put the slides in the
Google Drive for the workshop because
the font's really small?
>> Is it possible for
>> Can you just drop the slides in the
Google Drive for the workshop so we can
follow along on the screen?
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, you want me to do that
now?
>> Uh yeah, if you wouldn't mind though.
>> So, where is the Google Drive for the
workshop? Uh so the other is
>> uh are you going to share a link in uh
>> is it too small to see?
>> Yeah. Okay. Apologies. Uh
>> if you send it to me via airplane.
>> Yeah. First thing I need to do is
connect to the Wi-Fi.
>> I use AI.
>> Do you have the password?
>> AIT.
>> Oh
>> security. Yeah, we've done it.
[laughter]
[clears throat]
>> And I think it's connected. Okay, cool.
And
>> I think I'm
>> There we go.
>> I am a noob at this. So, let's see.
Uh yeah, if you want to share with me
Alan Tesla
or
>> Oh, contact only.
>> Okay. How do I find someone on this? I
don't usually use this.
>> Or if you if you want to share that. Is
that
>> share the link?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, this is fine.
>> Or just hit hit my
>> Ah, yeah. Let's go.
>> Al
tsl.io.
Excellent.
>> That's me. Came up.
>> There you go. And I'll drop it in
>> drop in the thing.
>> I will drop the link in the discord.
>> Okay, that's a good like five minute
break. Um,
thanks a lot for mentioning that as
well. The fellow that actually mentioned
that and that is my worry for the for
the workshop. It might be the screen
might be too small to see all the cool
logs and whatnot, but we'll try our
best. Um, okay. Very quickly, uh, very
quick question. Are you guys having fun?
>> That's good. And got a question. Alan,
we got to use Mac. Let's go. No, no,
it's good. It's good.
>> Hello. Uh, quick question. Um, uh, I
know we're talking about memory
engineering. the more I hear about it,
it's part of a cost issue, but if costs
aside, is that not just building or
expanding upon the model itself, like
training, you're almost like training
the model, but not it's just like, you
know, outside of it is
>> Yeah. So,
because obviously building a model is
very expensive. Is this
>> Yeah. So, what you're saying is is
memory engineering just training the
model like fine-tuning? Yeah, I guess
because you could all the memory here
you could take that data right and then
>> exactly you can use
>> put it in the model itself. So memory
engineering is one thing is this space
is still developing and you're you're
spot on which is eventually where it's
going to get to is
continuous learning right we we had this
already in machine learning so it's not
new right um back in the day I say back
in the day I'm not old I'm actually
quite young I think um I'm I'm I'm in my
30s um back in the day we used to have
these things called feature stores right
and they allowed for online learning
where you could uh solve issues is like
model drift right so we used to have
this for traditional machine learning
model we're going to have that in in um
LLM right in generative models very soon
they're large and the latency in is
quite huge and there's a lot of compute
required to actually retrain them but we
are going to get there today the memory
engineering I'm presenting to you is
actually half of the job to be done
because what we're doing is very simple
we have this three components of agent
memory we have the external memory. We
have the um we have the context window
of the LLM and we have the parametric
memory within the LLM itself. But we're
not modifying the static parametric
memory within this memory engineering
scaffolding. Right? But eventually we
are going to get there and when I do
this talk next year we're going to be
talking about that you could you could
fine-tune now actually but it's just the
time it takes right the amount of data
you need. But one thing cursor put out a
good blog last week that talk about um
that they're using the agent traces and
they're using that to fine-tune their
embedding models and they see uh
improvements in their semantic search.
So again obviously they have loads of
money to be able to do this but we can't
do this well I can but not your average
AI developer can't do this um on a
Jupyter notebook per se but we are going
to get there.
Good question.
>> The link is in the discord.
>> Excellent. Um, okay, let's go. So,
prompt engineering is
it's words about well, let me just
recap. So, we sp we said prompt
engineering is maximization. Context
engineering is optimization. Memory
engineering is both maximization and
optimization leading to continuation.
So, prompt engineering was words about
the world. And the reason why I have
this here is when I was creating the
slides and thinking about this topic
more in depth. I was really thinking
about how to distinguish how to how to
distinguish the differences between this
engineering disciplines, right? Um and
sometimes simplicity is the best way to
approach things. Uh I do have like an
over 10,000 word uh uh 10,000word essay
that I'm writing but this three lines
probably summarize the 10,000 words
essay which is prompt engineering is
words about the world right context
engineering is about world building and
then memory engineering is about world
persistence and the continuity of this
world that we're building for the LLM to
understand. So prompt engineering is
just about the words that we're using to
describe the word. The description is
key because if you change a bit of the
words, we found if you were if you were
to change certain words in your prompt,
um it changed the behavior of the LLM
and you change the output. So the
description aspect is key. Knowing what
linguistic patterns will actually get
you the right behavior from your LLM is
part of this whole evaluation um LLM
evaluation discipline as well. Then
context engineering is about not just
using the world about building the
context efficiently so your LLM could
understand this world that you're
building this problem domain then memory
engineering is the work that we are
going to do to make sure that the LLM is
the the world is persistent and it's
constantly persistent through all the
iterations. So let me ask the question
again.
How many of you agree with me on the
distinction between context engineering
and memory engineering?
Put your hands up if you agree with me.
Okay, we're increasing. That's good.
We're making progress. Again, I fail if
no one agrees with me. I also fail if
you all agree with me. So, I'm going to
ask it a couple more times. Um, people
always used to ask me, Rachel, when does
data become memory? And I have this line
in the next slide.
I this line didn't start off here. It
started off way here. But eventually as
I began to understand more and more, I
moved it further and I began to see the
capabilities of the infrastructure that
we have today. Let me explain. So there
is this memory engineering life cycle.
If you read any white paper on sessions
or memory or context engineering,
they're going to talk about this life
cycle. and is is I don't want to say
simple but it's easy to understand right
so we have data sources um external data
sources we're going to collect them
ingest them clean them do all the data
science stuff we used to do back in the
day then the next aspect of things that
we tend to do is we create different
representation of this data and the most
common one that we have within
generative AI today is embeddings vector
embeddings we take data pass it through
an embedded model and we get the
numerical representation of that data
and the numerical representation has
captured the semantics of the data. So
we have embeddings that you can couple
with the data and you can then ingest
that into a database like Oracle AI
database where you'll be able to do
things like semantic search using vector
search or you can do hybrid search which
is a combination of vector search with
any of the other search that we enable
within a database. Then another aspect
and this is the part where we start to
see why memory engineering is important.
Another aspect is the organization of
information. Data modeling is a topic I
should have paid more attention to when
I was at university because it's
important now. How you structure
information is actually important to
both the understanding of data and to
the LLM itself. Organization is
organization of information does
improves the performance of an LLM if
you actually think about it. Right? So
we'll talk more about this organization
factor of of um of the context window
but organization of information which
can be data modeling the information
that you put in your database
organization of information that you're
putting in the context window as well.
um Anthropic's piece which is titled
context engineering and I don't remember
the rest of it but type in anthropic
context engineering they have a good
image that shows the ideal organization
of the context window maybe for their
models and the piece that uh Google just
put out last week called context
engineering as well um sessions and
memory they also have like uh uh
explanation of the ordering of items
within a context window the key thing
here is organization is important.
Retrieval retrieval is then in the
pipeline as well. How do we get the
information out of the the database,
right? Again, there are two things which
is vector search is not all you need,
right? Uh vector search is a good
technique and you should use it, but you
shouldn't rely on it or think is the
sole way of retrieving information. Um,
I know there was the rave about vector
search and vector databases, but we
quickly realized that we needed robust
retrieval mechanisms to make our our AI
agents and the LLM accurate, which
essentially means reduce elucination
essentially. And one thing and one thing
is it's becoming very obvious but
another another thing that happened this
year and late last year was um
especially with coding assistance using
tools like like searching through files
using GP or using bash command to just
search for keywords within certain file
became almost seen as a replacement for
doing forms of database retrieval. But
again, the best one, I don't want to say
the best, but one of the companies in
the front line of coding assistants,
they put out a blog last week saying,
"Hey, we're not just using uh searching
through files, right? Using typical uh
search tools, we're actually using
semantic search enabled by database as
well." And this this and semantic search
and using a combination of both performs
better. Retrieval is a key aspect. Then
you have this you have this part over
here serialization whatever we want to
call it. But the key thing here is we're
taking the information from the context
window and putting it back into our data
store essentially to repeat this loop
here again. But that's the key thing.
This is like the memory engineering life
cycle. You call it the memory life cycle
but this is what what I'm seeing. Then
eventually we're going to put the whole
aspect of retraining the model uh the
LLM itself or even retraining the
embedded model within this life cycle as
well. I'm going to update the slides in
a few months. So the the question was
Richmond when does data become memory?
Because you've used the word memory a
lot right that's what a lot of people
used to say um earlier on when I used to
talk about this topic back when it
wasn't accepted propaganda like it is
today. Um people used to say Richmond
yeah when when does data become memory
or what's the difference between data
and memory? Um spoiler alert memory is
data and the point where we start to see
data becoming memory is usually when you
see the information being transformed
and represented in a different format.
That's when you begin the understanding
of it as memory. It helps when you're
building an AI agent. If you think about
information as something that is to be
remembered but also something that is
meant to be forgotten um it helps when
it helps when you're building the agent
this agentic systems okay so prompt
engineering maximization context
engineering optimization memory
engineering continuation I am not going
to say that those paragraphs there I
can't remember them and they're too
extensive okay so this is the this is
the journey we're on right prompt
engineering, context engineering, memory
engineering. We've mentioned a bunch of
keywords and I think I hope have hit on
those keywords. So if you look at them
when you have the slides, they'll become
very obvious to you. Now we can go into
the workshop in code. And that took
about 45 minutes to explain. So the key
thing is not what what I'm trying to get
across to you today is not to give you a
solved solution but to give you
essentially the scaffolding of thinking
of a scaffolding of thinking um a
scaffolding for thinking about what is
going to be one of the most relevant
aspects of aging engineering or AI
engineering or software engineering
within the next six to one year 6 months
to one year. And it's six months to one
year because I'm hoping everyone is
doing their job right because we need to
solve memory very quickly and I think
within the next year we'll have very
very solid solution to agent memory. So
you can call me when I did a talk um
about agent memory. The first one I did
it was
I think it was earlier this year. It was
in Greece and I I tried to make it cool
and I I I told a story about Prometheus.
Does anyone know the Greek mythology of
Prometheus? Put your hands up if you
know. That's a lot of people. That's
crazy. [laughter] Um so yeah, I was in
Greece. I was like, "Oh yeah, let me be
cool and talk about Greek mythology."
Prometheus obviously um Prometheus
essentially gave man fire and he got
punished for that for eternity, I think.
Correct me if I'm wrong. Um, but we got
punished for giving man fire. And fire
in the sense of intelligence to be able
to build tools and obviously flourish.
I'm not saying I'm Prometheus,
but [laughter]
anyway, so we're going to talk going
into the workshop and code and hopefully
I don't get punished for it. That's
weird. Um, we're going to talk about
memories. Again, it's a the name is a
joke. It's not like the official name.
Um, we're going to talk about the agent
stack. We're going to talk about
keywords like memory core and memory
layer um or memory provider as well. So
to find the code and this is small I
apologize but I hope you have the slides
you can type in memoriz GitHub on Google
and I hope the library comes up as the
first link. When you go into this repo,
you'll be able to see go into the
examples folder and you're able going
you're going to be able to see a single
agent um folder within the examples
folder and then you guys can click on
the local one and go through the process
of building an uh agent augmented with
memory. I'll take a pause there. Do we
have any questions?
>> Should we grab a quick coffee? And I
also need to mention lunch is at 12 over
at the 52A. Just like in case your
tummies are rumbling, that's where lunch
will be at 12. But if you want to grab a
coffee while we're doing this.
>> Yeah, dude.
>> I don't drink coffee, but I have water.
So,
>> you're good.
>> Yeah, [laughter]
>> the smell of coffee makes me want to
throw.
>> Uh, but yeah, dive in. And if anyone has
any difficulty getting hold of uh the
slides or Clooney the Reaper or anything
like that, just grab me or Richard and
we can point you in the right direction.
>> Excellent. So,
>> thanks.
>> I'll go over some propaganda. I'm
joking. I'll go over some of the some of
the slides and then we can get an
understanding of the repo and we can get
I'll go through some of the code as
well. Um, okay. So, the key thing here
is we're all learn to learn. So, you can
ask me questions. If you disagree with
me, say you disagree with me. I don't
mind. I won't cry. Um, but you can also
reach out to me on LinkedIn. Um, I'm
responsive sometimes. Uh, and uh, we can
have a good chat of agent memory and
memory engineering. And if you reach out
to me on LinkedIn and I ignore you is
because I'm probably doing a talk like
this. I'm preparing for it as well,
which usually takes a couple weeks, but
do reach out on LinkedIn. So, this is
again small to see. I apologize, but if
you have the slides in front of you, you
can go for it. Let's talk about the
agent stack. So there are a couple
components within agent memory that are
just staple, right? And you have a bunch
of people that operate within the this
the layers of agent stack. Um the key
I'm just I'm not going to go through
each one, but I'll just talk about the
key one. So we have the communication
and protocol layer, right? This is your
MCPs, A2A, uh what's the one from IBM
called? Is it called ACP?
I think so. I'm not sure.
>> What number are you on?
>> Uh I'm on slide number 46.
>> Oh, you guys are on the slides. Wow. Um
okay. Uh there was another question.
>> No, my inner thoughts. Okay, so we have
the communication and protocol layer,
right? This is where your protocols A2A
um MCP actually stay reside within. But
one thing we're doing in Oracle is we
saw the emergence of loads of different
frameworks and the engineering team at
Oracle
actually looked at a key thing which is
how can we standardize agents across all
of this framework so that you can take
an agent built in like Cai and move it
port it over to Langraph. The best way
that they describe this is um the onyx
framework which we used back in the day
to use the same model built in PyTorch.
You could use that same model using the
onyx model within um uh TensorFlow once
upon a time. Um but again um I joined
Oracle
two weeks ago
and I could see like there was this
amazing engineering um effort to try to
standardize and really bring agent
engineering to the forefront of AI
developers.
Hence why I'm here. Hence why I'm at
Oracle. And the open agent spec is very
interesting to me because I knew we we
had to I've worked in other database
companies and I knew that the way we
solve a lot of the different attempts at
making agents work in production is to
think about how we can standardize it
standardize this. So Enthropic did it
well with MCP and Oracle. They're trying
to figure out how to standardize the
porting of agents across frameworks.
So that's the communication on protocol
layer. You can check it out the open
agent spec. There's a paper that we
wrote and you can check it out there. So
there is this orchestration layer,
right? That is where your frameworks and
library live. Langraph um you have folks
like uh hstack that operate within this
layer as well. Then there's the
reasoning layer which is the LLM. This
is the model provider. This is where
they live. Then you have the memory
layer. So I'm going to explain the
memory layer. It's going to it sounds
weird but the memory layer is
the scaffolding that we do in memory
engineering but a bunch of very helpful
engineers have abstracted away a lot of
this common techniques and process. So
example of that like I saw a lot of
hands up is mezero right mem zero is a
memory management layer. Langme, check
it out from the team at Langchain.
That's a memory management layer. Um,
Cognney is another one. Meg GPT is
another one. And a couple of them are
popping up. There's one that I saw that
raised a crazy amount and it's called
Super Memory, right? Anyone did anyone
hear about Super Memory? Hands up if you
did. Some hands up. Just one. But yeah,
more are popping up. I think we're going
to see more from maybe the model
providers pop up uh as we go through uh
the year as well. Then the memory core
is different from the memory layer. So
the memory core essentially is the
database itself is the store where the
information is stored, right? It gives
you all the retrieval mechanisms for
really pulling information out. And what
memory layers typically do is they help
you engineer all of the different memory
types that we've spoken about. The way
that the data is modeled and the way
data is retrieved as well. They abstract
this away from you. So Zep is a popular
one as well. Has anyone heard about Zep?
Hands up if you've heard about Zep.
Nice. They they're very big on the
knowledge graph space. So
they those tools abstract this
complexity of understanding the memory
types and understanding how to retrieve
information. They abstract that so that
you guys can get to production very
quickly. Um which is obviously a good
way to go and it's the same thing I'm
trying to do with memories. memories
like I said at the beginning of this is
it was a way to prove a point as to
where this field is going in terms of
the work that we have to do as AI
engineers or AI memory engineers um and
you should not use it in production
actually I actually have that in the
read me don't use in production but it's
a learning tool so you can look for the
code and learn from it okay so that is
the difference between memory layer a
bunch of engineering um and programmatic
code to actually move information and
model data. Then you have the memory
core which is your database that will
give you all the retrieval methods and
storage and all the compute you need.
Then there's the obvious infrastructure
layer as well which is the agile compute
and inference and all the good stuff. So
that is the agent stack. I'm going to
update this a bit. I feel like we can
consolidate some of these layers as
well. This is memoriz. Uh you could type
in memoriz at GitHub or you could just
go into the link on the next slide.
Let's see. Oh, that was the last slide.
You go to the link on the previous
slide, this slide over here. Go into the
examples and into the local folder and
you'll be able to go through the
notebook there. Okay,
let's go into some code. And it's going
to be small. Can you guys see this?
Let's see.
Uh let's try this.
Tell me you guys can see this. No. Okay.
Just a little bit.
>> There's no local folder.
>> There's no what?
>> No local folder in examples.
[clears throat]
>> Let me verify that.
>> I see deep research.
>> Yeah. Single agent.
>> There's a single agent and there's a me
agent
local. There you go. So you can just run
that and what that would do is um you
guys can't see the code. A part of me
want wants to do something which is
bring you guys all up to the front and
watch me execute this and I think you'll
be able to see it.
>> Yeah. So those of you who want are very
interested, you can come up to the
front. Um are there pillows? I'm joking.
Um but we can like just sit down here or
just stand here and just watch me. It's
going to be fun.
You just bring your chairs to the front.
>> Nah, you need to sit on the floor.
[laughter]
You got to make it like cozy, man. No,
I'm joking. Bring your chairs to the
front. That was a better suggestion than
I had. I was going for pillows.
[laughter]
Okay. Um, cool. Don't be shy, guys.
This is going to be the best workshop.
>> All right, let's go. So if you run
through this notebook, I'm going to show
you two notebooks and we could go
through it very quickly. If you go
through this notebook, you're actually
going to have you're actually going to
install the Oracle AI database on your
local and you'll be able to run through
the step. So you can install this using
Docker and I've kept as much instruction
as possible to make sure this is a
seamless I hate using the word seamless
because Chachet loves that word, but
this is a seamless experience for you.
Um feel free to go to the link. The key
thing is and let me just start this. We
could start with the first.
So again you can there are two ways you
can do this within the memories library
there's a CLI. So when you actually in
pip install the package pip install
memories you actually get a CLI with it
and you can use a CLI within your own
particular within your own setup your
own environment. So let's start with
this. So you're going to pip install.
Let me increase this again until it gets
uncomfortable. Okay, we're going to
install uh pip install memories and
we're going to also install Oracle DB.
That's going to be our memory core. Then
we're going to use open AI as well. I do
have some examples that show how to use
some of the models from hugging face uh
with the memories library. So we're
going to start running this and there's
nothing exciting happening here. We're
just running a bunch of stuff. So
that's good. So part one part one of
this notebook is just the setting up of
Oracle AI database. And the key thing
we're doing here is we're just going to
be I have a Docker container running.
Let me clear all this outputs actually
so we can Yeah. So this is what the a
CLI command is going to look like. So
memories install Oracle. I'm going to
add more memory providers um as I'm
permitted to. Then you would just run
maybe uh let's see when you run this
very quickly it's if you don't have um
docker run it's going to tell you docker
is not running but it will also just
install the Oracle um image for Oracle
AI database image which should take
around 1 GB within your local memory.
There is a full version of the Oracle AI
database that takes around 9 GB but it
takes longer to install. If you would
like to install the full one, I uh you
just actually just do this uh d-4 and
that will install the full version for
Oracle AI database. But the light one is
enough. So once you actually run this
command in the output, you're going to
see a bunch of information for your
environment variables. Question.
>> Uh so you mentioned 9 GB for the the
database size. um is that you found that
be plenty for for all the agent work
you've been doing or does it need to be
expanded out much larger or anything
like that?
>> So the the local installation the light
version is just for you to get started.
It's not meant to be used particularly
in production.
>> Again the thing about Oracle database is
the enterprisegrade security. We work
with a lot of Fortune 500 company and
the full one has a bunch of these
enterprise grade securities right but to
get started quickly we created a light
version. So you could just install it
less time to download
but check out Oracle cloud for if you
want if you actually have production
workload and you can just follow the
same steps. That's why within the same
notebook there's a mem agent remote
where you just put in your connection um
details and it just connects to Oracle
cloud database.
Any questions? So is 9 GB on the hard
drive or just like in the docker
>> you said 9 GB of memory
>> pardon 9 gigs of memory
>> nine gigs of memory for the full one
around 9 gigs don't
>> but for this workshop it's not going to
take up that much
>> it's not going to take up that yeah yeah
it's not
>> good clarification [laughter]
>> okay so when you actually run this
you're going to have your um admin
password in the output and what you can
do is just get that in there we need to
get that into your environment and
that's what the cell does. Nothing
special is happening there. This just
allows us to connect to the Oracle
database. So the next thing we're going
to do is we've installed the Oracle AI
database within our local machine. Now
we need to set it up. And when we what
we mean by setting it up is creating a
memories user, creating all the tables
and vector indexes that we need. And
again, the CLI solves this memories set
up Oracle. And it's going to do a bunch
of stuff. um clean. It's going to kill
any sessions if they already exist and
start a new one. And you can see here
it's just creating executing a bunch of
statements and creating a bunch of
indexes and it's done very quick. And if
you don't want to go through option one,
there is a manual installation where I
take you through all the steps where you
just start from scratch. And I think I
put a link to where you can get the
Docker image from somewhere. But we're
not going through option one. We're
going through We're going through option
one. We're not going for option two. So
now that we have Oracle AI database in
our local machine, what we can do is
next is start to get start to build our
mem agent. And I call agents built with
memories. I call them mem agent. Can
anyone guess why?
Memory agent. Mem agent. I'm bad with
names. Um whenever I write code, the
naming of my variable gets worse. Okay,
so just this is just for login. This is
for environment variables. It's going to
be so weird switching my screen to put
in my environment variables, but I'll
just delete them after. Okay, so we're
going to be using OpenAI for this. Um,
so you need to actually have an OpenAI
API key. Um,
can we switch this screen so I can get
my environment variables put in?
>> Nice.
I don't trust you guys. [laughter]
>> Password two.
>> Exactly. Uh pardon.
Um okay. So, uh we can switch back.
>> Nice. Um okay. So, here we go. So, one
thing we're going to do is we're going
to create uh Oracle configuration. And
that's just so we can create what I call
uh a memory provider. And Oracle is
going to be our memory provider in this
particular um in this particular
instance and Oracle AI database that's
the memory call. So this memory provider
is a bunch of is a bunch of abstracted
code for how to create indexes and how
to do the retrieval and the memory call
is Oracle AI database. So we have an
Oracle AI database uh we have the Oracle
provider initialized and you're going to
get a bunch of um information in the
logs as to what's happened. The key
thing is you want to see this when you
do the notebook and no errors. All
right. So this is the fun part. We can
just straight away build an agent.
Actually I I went too quick to do that.
So let me explain this code within
memories right
right here. Apologize for the cough. uh
within memories we can actually we
actually have builders builder module
where we can we have this abstracted
class called mem agent builder and that
will just build a very simple agent for
you. So we're going to initialize
something called again the name is bad.
It's it's the name of this agent is
agent builder made bad naming but the
key thing is we're creating an agent
using the me agent builder. We're going
to set it with its core identity [cough]
using the width instruction. We can just
give it like a system prompt
essentially, right? Then the
infrastructure of it, we're going to set
it with the memory provider that we set
earlier on which is Oracle. And then
we're going to give it a bunch of LLM
configuration. So memories will
recognize um embedded models from
OpenAI. Um but this is the LLM. So we
also recognize um LLM from OpenAI as
well and the hog face as well. So you
need your open AI key and you just call
the build method and that's done. So,
one thing you're going to notice is
this.
There's a bunch of logs, but I'm already
adding tools to the agent when you
actually initialize it. Um, and the
reason why I'm doing this, you can see
the tools here. I'm just going to scroll
in.
And you can look all of this code is
open source. So, you can see what is
being done and how I'm doing it. The
first tool is context window stats tool.
Like I mentioned earlier in this talk,
the agent, every agent we initialize
actually has awareness of the context
window length. So it can then auto
summarize, right? So it doesn't fall
into the context bloat or exceed the
context threshold. Cursor does this
automatically and they have the GBT
codeex actually does this as well.
They've got like a little meter that you
can see. Then there's another [cough]
there's another tool list summary
registry tool just whenever we do the
auto summarization I want to be able to
see existing summaries and actually
fetch the summary and also look up
entities and insert entities because
this agent is going to interact with
other um other entities whether within
the context I provide it or the context
it has when it's interacting with it
environment. So automatically it can
actually um it actually stores entities
it interacts with in its memory store.
Um this this library is a bit
opinionated but very quickly we've
initialized an agent with this different
memory conversational memory long-term
memory persona. So we've initialized
this agent with those type of memory and
it's been built successfully. And
I can store everything in Oracle AI
database. [cough]
If you're watching this back on YouTube,
the coffin is so annoying. I hope this
is edited somehow. Um, okay. So when you
save it, we actually store the and again
memories is my personal project. It's
not an official product from Oracle. So
just wanted to put the disclaimer out
there. Um when you actually store this,
we actually store the agent information
in the database and we have a memory ID
for we have a single memory ID for a
bunch of agents.
And the reason why we store it is
because we want to be able to load and
reuse agents within different
environment just by taking pulling in
information from the database that's
been stored to actually then load it
within another environment.
So, we're going to start building an
agent. So, we're going to build this
agent. Um, agent builder. We've already
built Sorry, we've already built our
agent. We've saved our agent and it's
called agent builder made. Terrible
name. Um, we're just going to run it and
I'm just going to say, "Hello, my name
is Alice. My name is not Alice. My name
is Richmond." Um, but for this example,
my name is Alice and I I love hiking in
the mountains. And we're going to see
its response.
And you can see very quickly I'm just
going to we're just going to go through
the the output actually very quickly and
don't worry about the speed. There is no
quantization and I'm not trying to optim
optimize for latency here. Um and I
should have probably kept streaming as
well but very quickly we're going to go
through the logs. Um what we can see
here is first we're loading information
but there's zero conversation within
previous interaction. So that we've
loaded zero conversational memory and
you can see that we're able to see
what's in the context window. So we've
used 513
um tokens with the with the existing 128
length of the context window. But now
what we've now done is we're executing
the tool and we're inserting an entity
in the entity memory named Alice. The
entity type is a person and it has the
attri attribute favorite memory hiking
in mountains and it's doing this
automatically because it has the entity
memory. Now our agent is going to
remember me uh Alice and it's going to
be able to update its information about
Alice. Now we're executing this tool
look up. We're looking at the we're
retrieving the memory and we're passing
it back into the context window. That's
why you see this increase in the context
window length. But very quickly, the
agent says, "Hello, Alice. It's great to
meet you. I've noted that you love
hiking in the mountain. If there is
anything specific you would like to talk
about or yeah, blah, blah, blah." Um,
but you get the point, right? Right out
of the box, you have an agent that can
remember a certain entity that has
interacted with within um its execution
and stores it within a dedicated um
memory store. But also, you have an
agent that can just use tools. And these
tools are also I never mentioned but
these tools are stored in a database
right the JSON schema for these tools
are stored in the database and the agent
can just use the right tools it requires
using some form of a vector search
operation the way I do it is I take the
dock string of the tools I create an
embedding for it I store it into the
database for every query I look at the
vector similarity then I'm able to
select just the tools I need rather than
giving it all the tools I have that make
sense it makes it easier so you don't
bloat the context.
>> So that's right.
>> It's coming. It's coming.
>> Okay. Uh so for this example obviously
like you're passing the memory, you
know, context as plain text. I could
imagine a more complex example where you
want it to be structured, right? Like
have you tested that out? Do you support
that in the demo library? Like what's
sort of the the differentiation here?
>> Yeah. So your your question is I'm
sending all the information uh into the
LLM as text,
>> right? Is is is how you
>> Yeah. Like why would you do that rather
than to say like Dave Alice?
>> Dave Alice
>> like name Alice.
>> Name Alice,
>> right? Rather than saying my name is
Alice. I'm an LLM.
>> Oh, the reason why I'm saying hello, my
name is Alice is just the input prompt,
right? It's just a It's just an example
of how you interact with LLM through
text, right? Is is am I getting a
question wrong here?
>> I I was thinking more like if you're
building this sort of um
tool to create memory for the agents,
right? Yeah. Like
>> I could imagine a world where you don't
want to put all of the memory as
playing, right? You want to create like
a agent that is barebone and just give
it the memory the memory it needs. The
memory types it needs. You can do that
here. I'm just showing one that builds
everything. I'm building memories for
fun obviously not production use but I'm
building it for every memory type to be
a standalone. So you would use a tool
like langraph and you would then use
entity memory from memories and only use
that particular memory.
>> Right. So you just add it as a tool for
the langraph agent to use.
>> Okay. So just for demo purposes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Sorry it took a while
for me to gro that. [laughter]
Okay, let's go. So we went over this
speaking to the agent. The agent is
telling us stuff. And this is I'm trying
to demonstrate conversational memory,
but I've also gener uh demonstrated
entity memory as well. So let's just
see. I'm going to ask it what was my
name again. It should be able to
remember my name. Okay, cool. Your name
is Alice. So, we're running the same
agent and it remembers our name. So,
I've not done any extensive scaffolding
for it to remember my name or for it to
you can see it did like a entity memory
lookup, right? So, again, this is all of
this stuff is doing behind the scene
without having without having to without
having me having to write this extensive
code. You can see loaded previous
conversation entries. Before it loaded
zero, now it's loaded two cuz we've
interacted with it. That's
conversational memory. That's entity
memory. That's tool memory. And now you
have conversational memory. And that's
the response. Okay. Let's look at
persona. We spoke about persona. Um
personality essentially is what it
stands for. We have this uh memories has
the aspect of different long-term memory
types that we went through in the
slides. So we're going to look at how we
can get persona in. Um so this is a
prompt or this is just a text for a
persona description. And we're going to
make our agent a bit emo like and this
the reason why I'm doing this is not me
this is not my example but was it this
year or last year even this year last
year an April fool jokes from open AAI
was to create a emo GPT. So there was an
emoj called Monday within your chat GPT
interface and you could interact with it
and it gave you emo like answers like
sad sarcastic answers. But one thing you
could do is you can ask it to give you
its system prompt and this is it. It
actually gave you the system prompt when
you asked it. So I just copied and
pasted it. It was called Monday and I
think it was an April Fool's joke. Okay.
So
So I just took it. We're going to make
our agent a bit more sarcastic. And cuz
I'm bad of names, I named it Sunny. Um,
obviously contradictory, but we're going
to create within memories, you can
create a persona um object, and we're
just going to pass that into the
variable persona. And then we're going
to create a new agent. It's called
sarcastic agent, which is better than
the other agent's name. Um, with the
instruction your sarcastic and cynical
assistant, we're going to give it a
persona. You can see with persona pass
the persona in use the same memory
provider that we already configured and
the LLM configuration as well. We build
it great and this is a brand new agent
and it gets all the tools that it needs
and you can see it's been created and we
can store it in our database.
Now it's going to be persisted uh now
it's going to be persisted in the
database and we can ask it what is your
name and its name is Sunny. We specify
that in a persona and it's going to um
remember its name. So again, but you can
tell it's sticking to his persona
because h the age-old question that
haunts humanity. What what's in a name?
You can call me Sunny. He answers a
question, but it sticks to the persona
we gave it, which is it's sarcastic. So
it's a bit of a personality that we're
able to give our agents. Now, obviously,
you don't want to be using this in your
FAQ agents for your um for whatever
companies you work in, but again, I'm
going to tell it, hey, I I am Alice.
Nice to meet you. Just to show that we
still have this conversational memory
going on. And I'm going to ask it, what
was my name? And it says, oh, slipping
already. Don't worry, your secret is
safe with me. You're Alice. It
remembers. It's sarcastic. Has
conversational memory. It has entity
memory. Now, it has persona memory.
Right? Are you guys following this?
>> Nice. Okay, we're going to create
another persona. You can tell uh this
example is uh very long. So, I'm going
to then take a persona, but every agent
built with memories. You can actually
set a persona. So, we have this agent
builder made. I'm going to change the
name after this session. Agent builder
made agent. Um and we just call a set
persona method and pass in this persona
object that is called Moody. Um and this
is meant to be a Moody assistant.
So, I've already run this and it's uh
updated the existing agent. There's a
bit of error here, but that's fine. It
should still work. We're going to ask it
what is your name. Wow, then it just
died. Um, and it says I'm Moody because
we've set the persona to Moody, it
remembers and it's going to ask now it's
taken on this persona. Though I might
have a bit of mood about it sometimes.
What can I help you with today? So,
that's example of again persona memory.
Let's talk about toolbox memory. One of
the key things about LLMs is they have
this emerging abilities to actually um
call the right tools at the right time.
So, we're going to give the agent a
couple of tools. So, one of the tool
well we're going to give it one tool.
We're going to create a weather agent.
We're going to use create a function
called get weather. We're going to give
it um a string a dock string that
describes the function. And then we're
going to just use a simple request to
this particular API endpoint. And we're
going to pass in the latitude and
longitude and that will give us uh the
uh the weather uh particularly the
degree the temperature within a certain
location. So we're going to build a
weather agent, right? You guys can see
the pattern here. We're going to give it
the instruction, but now we're going to
add it with tool get weather. So we're
passing a tool into it. And we obviously
we have a memory provider and we have
the with LLM. And what happens is
now this agent has access to this tool
because when we save it, we store a JSON
schema of the tool in the database
attached to the agent. Right? We have a
referential ID of the agent ID attached
to where we've stored the tool JSON
schema. So I'm going to ask you, what's
the weather like in New York? This is
actually sick. And I'll tell you why
this is sick. I've done this example so
many times this year and this is the
first time I am actually doing it in New
York. [laughter]
So it's actually I just realized that
that's just mind-blowing. Um I'm based
in the UK live in London. All right. So
and you can see it works. So the weather
is 7.3°. Um excuse me. You can you go
outside and check if that's correct?
>> It's correct. [laughter]
>> I'm joking. Um okay. So yeah, here we
can see that he's able to use the tool.
It has awareness of the tool and it's
giving us this degrees in the the right
weather. And I'm just going to run it
again. Is it warmer in Los Angeles? And
you can see I'm not even passing in Oh,
I am passing in the longest latitude. I
shouldn't even do that. I don't need to
do that. This agent is smart. Well, just
in case it fails. You can see it says
yes, it's one way in Los Angeles, 11.8
compared to New York. Let's see. Even on
passing the coordinates actually we
still get this right because it has
conversational memory. Hm.
>> Open AI.
>> Pardon?
>> It's using Open AI. You said
>> Yeah, we already used um the LLM it
configuration is using Open AI, but you
can change it to uh hugging face if you
want. I have a an example that shows you
how to do that. But the weather a the
weather the actual weather information
is using um what's the name of this
endpoint I'm using? Uh met open Matteo.
Yeah.
>> Okay. Cool.
>> I have a question about
>> You go
>> about uh workflows which are very
common. uh the how would you suggest
memory works with like a series of tools
or a tool and an agent llm port and then
few other tools
>> you're asking about workflow memory
right so one thing that is actually
happening that you can't see is the the
execution is being stored in this
workflow memory right this agent in the
database we're actually storing within
the workflow table we're storing rows of
the execution so it actually has
information of the workflow that's been
executed
So I searched for this particular tool
using this parameters. This was the
result and the outcome was a success.
>> And if [clears throat] I want to
pre-bake certain uh workflows to the to
this entire thing, right? How how would
I engineer the memory so he would know
to go through a certain workflow when
you're being asked, I don't know,
something about the weather. Let's say,
yeah, give me the weather in the US and
then I want to do
New York and then whatever Los Angeles
and Florida.
>> So if I understand your question
correctly, how do you engineer the the
the
agent to be able to run multiple
queries?
>> Multiple more than that, right? like
when I'll ask them like the agent, hey,
I I just need the the weather in uh in
New York, uh the weather in the US, I
want them to I want the agent to return
specifically New York, LA, and Miami,
right? Like, and it's specific three
calls to the weather uh app and maybe
just like some comparison in between or
something like that. How would you? But
I wanted to answer that automatically
when I asked the weather about like like
the weather in the US.
>> I think I'm understanding your question.
>> So similar to the way that you would do
it in NA,
right? Like in in NAN you would go and
build like an ETL sort of graph around
it, right?
>> Can we do that with just memory saying
like hey
>> you can do that with just code, right?
you can actually implement the execution
step, right? NA10 is essentially just
code in a sense, but yeah, you could do
that with memory, you could do that with
code. And I apologize I'm not
understanding this question correctly.
So, I'm going to what's your name?
>> Oro.
>> Oro, I'm going to talk to you after this
to make sure that we can talk and I
understand what you're answering.
If I don't, you can come to the UK and
find me.
Okay. So, let's talk about semantic
cache and just watching time because I'm
in between you and lunch. I'm joking.
I'm just hungry. But, um, okay. So,
let's go in this. We're just going to
look at semantic cache. I've already
explained what semantic cashier is. So,
and we've already built different agents
multiple times.
But the key thing I'm doing right here
is every agent that has been built so
far has an aspect of semantic cache.
I've not just told you. Um, so one thing
and the way you can see that is let me
just make sure. Yeah, there we go. This
is the semantic cache section. And one
thing we can just see that is I'm going
to ask it again a question. The time
taken is 1.4 seconds. And I remove this
output that shows when it has a cache
hit. I'm going to ask it the same
question. Um,
just to test this again. Let me see. The
output of a semantic cache hit doesn't
show, which is terrible. So that doesn't
help. Uh I apologize for that. One thing
I'm going to be able to do is we're
going to enable semantic cache within
this agent now. And when I ask it this
cell below, what's the capital of
France?
We're just going to calculate the time
it takes.
Right? So it says the capital of France
is Paris. That's great. We're going to
ask it again. What's the capital of
France? It takes a shorter time because
it's returning a cache response. Right?
That shows semantic cache. It doesn't
show it show it well but let me there's
another example uh there is no cash hit
here if I ask it tell me France capital
in small caps even though it's the same
agent there's no there is no cash hit
and it's giving us the same [cough]
giving us the uh a different answer even
though the same answer as before is
Paris what I'm going to do is tell me
the funds capital in small caps the
what's another word for small what's a
cinnamon for small
>> tiny tiny Tiny in tiny caps.
What other options did people
>> lowerase
>> minus school lower case? Yeah, low lower
case is more developer aligned.
Let's see lowerase cap. Okay. See
returning cash response because lowerase
and small again very semantically
similar. We'd have to go to the LLM. It
takes a shorter time and we don't pay
open AI.
>> Do you have a question?
>> What type of G are you using? I'm using
Oracle AI database as a database.
>> Yeah, it's it's obviously not the most
optimal, but just showing the example.
We have another cache feature called
true cache. You can check it. Oracle
true cache.
>> But here's just showing how you can use
your database as that memory call.
>> So this is AI open.
>> No. So this call, this specific call
didn't have to go to open AI because we
already stored the response. We stored
the previous query when we add it as
small right in the database and we
generated an embedding of this query in
the database when we made it when it was
small. So when I when we changed it to
lowercase what we did was just vector
search right we did a vector distance
calculation and this query and the
previous query are semantically similar
and then I have a threshold score which
means if it's within a certain range
let's say 0.8 eight to to one which
represents how similar it is just use
the stored response from the previous
execution rather than going to the open
AI to get me the information because
it's going to be the same information
brought back open AI to determine where
semantic is
>> you need open AI for the first iteration
right for the first execution right you
need to actually go get the LLM response
>> right
>> but for anything else
>> no but once you change it to lowerase
>> yeah once I change to lower case How
does it know? What do you How does it
know to semantically similar without
open AI?
>> No, we don't go to Well, we technically
we do go to open AI because we have to
generate the embeddings.
>> Okay.
>> But that's Yeah, we generate the
embeddings using open AI.
>> Okay.
>> Right. Yeah. Is is that what you're
asking?
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> You're still using Open You're not
bypassing Open AI in this case.
>> I'm not bypassing Open AI. I'm
generating embedded using Open AI, but
I'm not going to the LLM. I'm not going
to GPT.
>> Right. So, I guess that should be very
clear as I should make that very clear
next time. I am generating embeddings
but I am not making an inference call.
>> Uh doesn't this introduce security
concerns for multi-tenant applications?
>> Yeah, it does. So you definitely have to
the I'm saying this memories does,
right? The library memories does. That's
what I mean because hey, don't use this
in production. This is me learning. But
there are robust um product features
that we offer. Like I mentioned, we have
Oracle True Cache which has all of the
security enterprisegrade security
standards you expect. But don't use this
memories library because it doesn't have
all of that in the library.
Okay. So last one I want to show is
summarization and it'll be we'll be
right on time. Ah let's skip
summarization. I apologize. Let's skip
summarization so I can show you deep
research, right? Um, just very quick,
summarization is you take the long
context, you summarize it, store it
somewhere, and you can use the
summarization to update the persona as
well. Um, apologies for not going for
it. I just wanted to go through this
deep research example.
So, I am not going to Damn it. I have to
can we take the screen so I can open my
uh pass in my keys and I'll let you know
when we are good to get that in there.
Thank you. Uh let's go.
So we need the open AI key and one more
key before we put it back in.
I'm going to be using Tavi for my
search. So deep research obviously we
want to be searching different um URL.
We're good to go. All right. So, kept in
all the keys. I'm using OpenAI as the
LLM. I'm using Tavi. Have you guys heard
of Tavi?
>> Excellent. So, I'm going to be using
Tavi for the internet search. And um
we're just going to be actually creating
all the steps we did before. But here,
you can switch the model to a hogface
model if you want. Um and you can also
switch the um embedded model as well to
a hogface embedded model. you can switch
the model later to a hogenface model. So
if you want to if you if you want to run
this locally, you can just use this. You
can use the hogenface LLM config and
just pass that in into the provider
itself.
I will show where you can do that later.
The key thing is we have this Tavi
provider which built into memories. It
gives us internet access and you need
that for deep research because deep
research is basically you have a prompt
that maybe initializes an agent that can
do a bunch of extensive uh analysis and
one of that could be going into a link
right and then you want to go into
another link that maybe citation within
the other link and embed as deep as you
want to go but I have some configuration
to just set max results from the search
that we do. I'm using tably to do web
crawling and also searching um searching
the internet as well. I have this boiler
function called build agent and we can
create this deep research agent specify
tavity as the internet provider and
create all the other configuration
and now is the part I actually want to
get to is what agents are we going to
build. We're going to this is a multi-
aent system right so we're going to have
the root agent. The root agent is the
where the query comes in. Um, and the
query is going to be an Apple Apple.
This is a um analyst uh agent. So, we're
going to use the build agent uh code
that we wrote earlier. We're going to
pass in the instruction that we want to
give it and we're going to give it more
specific details about what we expect it
to do. Assign task, monitor progress,
and coordinate symphysis. Then, we're
going to have this uh delegate. We're
going to have a root agent has delegate.
So the way I call multi- aent it will
make sense later is we have a root agent
and we have delegates and delegates are
other agents that report to the root
agent. So we have three delegates. So we
have this financial delegate, market
delegate and a risk delegate and they
each have their own responsibility and
then we have a synthesis agent which
will essentially synthesize all the
reports and get back to the user. So we
save all of these agents in our
database. we've done in the previous
notebook several times, you guys know it
now. So, we're just going to do this and
you can look at the logs. It's adding
all the function and the tools. So, all
of these agents have their own tools,
their own their own um capabilities as
well and their own memory um stores as
well. Now, we have this deep research
orchestrator where we set the root agent
to the root agent we specified the
delegates to the free delegates that we
have over here and the symphysis
agent such a difficult word. Um, and we
just pass in the symphysis agent. And
then we run this. And I'm just going to
pass in this query to provide a freeear
stock analysis for Apple. Um,
highlighting financial trends, market
dynamics, and key risk. And that's the
prompt. And we can put it in deep
research mode. You can see the output.
Spoiler alert. Um, spoiler alert. But
there's a bunch of logs just showing
what's going on here. Um you can see it
knows the number of delegates that it
has and it's analyzing the delegates
capability so it can give the right
delegates the right queries to execute
and it's just it might take a bit of
time but you can see here we're using
Tavali to search the internet for a
particular query and we're looking at
the results of that query we're storing
it passing that into the context window
of the LLM saying hey here is the
results from the search result and it's
just going to carry on the work at the
end of this when all the roots all the
deleg ates are done. So the job of the
root agent is to understand the query
and then delegate it to the right agent,
right? Parts of the query to the right
agent. Then when the delegate agents are
done, they go into the symphysis agent
and say, "Hey, here's my work." The job
of the symphysis agent is to compile all
of this and give us the output. It's
still running. Um, deep research can be
extensive. Um but yeah it's extensive
because it's traversing through a bunch
of links and conducting a bunch of
searches and the report looks something
like this just for the sake of time you
will get oh it's done. So
yeah, so we just got the report and it's
just like a like an essay essentially.
Not an essay, a short essay covering all
what we wanted. It's given us all the
right information. Gone to the internet
to search for this information. I was
asking for the financial information of
each quarters of Apple and it's just
gotten me the right information from
internet search. Deep research.
Okay. Was that fun?
Yeah.
>> Was it boring or was it fun? It
>> was good.
>> It was good. Yeah, you guys. Okay. I'm
about to change it up. We would do maybe
workflow agent next. All right. So, I
want to ask a question one last time.
Um, you guys can guess the question I'm
going to ask, right? Do you guys
agree with me on the clear distinction
between context engineering and memory
engineering? Put your hands up if you
agree with me.
Yes, that's good. I I'll take that. I'll
take that. That's better than what we
started off with. We started off with
three. Now we're I would say maybe 15 or
so. Um that's it guys. That's all I got
for you. Thank you for spending two
hours of me. [applause]
>> Any final questions? Anyone?
>> Final final questions before we leap out
the room.
>> Final question right down there.
>> This might be a little orthogonal to
something demo, but I wonder.
>> Sorry. This might be a little bit more
orthogonal to uh the demo and what you
were presenting, but uh you mentioned
episodic memory. What's a good use case
for actually using episodic memory if
you can synthesize all of the other
information using the other different
types of memory? I'm assuming that
you're the orchestration and the actual
methodology in which you arrived at the
answer allows you to generalize the task
the agent, but I'm wondering like how
you use it.
>> How do I use episodic memory? So sorry
say the last bit again.
>> Uh what use cases?
>> What use cases would you use episodic
memory
>> right? Generally when you have
assistance
uh I don't know if you were here at the
beginning by identified free application
mode you you were at the beginning so
when you have an assistant agent right
you want to use episodic memory there
are different type of episodic memory.
Of course you could generalize you could
summarize that's what you mean by
generalize right you could summarize a
context window and store that somewhere.
Is that what you mean? Yeah, because if
you use I'm again I'm assuming right
like if you're using uh episodic memory
you're basically because you're storing
the entire process you're effectively
adding a lot more context that has to be
loaded into the model right but if you
synthesize it I'm assuming that you can
like you can basically deliver that
information faster without using uh like
some of that token
>> context so what do you mean by symph
>> um I was hoping this would be a short
question no it's
No, you might want to take this.
>> Yeah, I mean, I can just talk.
>> We're just nerding out here. We're just
going to
>> I I worry that the few everyone's going
to get restless.
>> We can we can carry on and I still got
to talk to Aro over there. So,
>> uh we we can turn off the mic. The the
session
>> the session is done.
>> I really appreciate this. Uh thank you
for sharing your slides and all the
information in the GitHub. Uh pounce on
Richard. He has a lot of experience and
a lot of interesting uh topics to talk
about. So, uh, pounce on Richard before
he leaves on a flight. You're here for
the rest of the day, are you not?
>> Yes, I'm here for the rest of the day.
>> So, uh, yeah, once again, thank you so
much, Richard, uh, Richmond for, uh,
joining us. And don't know what I'm
talking about. Uh, yeah, go on. I just
wanted to mention lunches that way, uh,
in 52A. Uh, and we'll start again after
lunch. Thank you so much,
>> [music]